Garemani Family Collection of Persian and Arabic Manuscripts and Books LSC.0453
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Manuscripts, ca. 1514-1899
  - 14 Kitab-i ?ibb-i ?akim-i Ma?i mawsum bih si bakhiyah The medical book of the former sage known as the thirty stitches., 1866. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    Scope and Content Note Medical text commonly attributed to author and calligrapher Murta?á Quli (Khan) Shamlu, son of ?asan Shamlu, 17th century ?afawid governor of Heart, in modern Afghanistan (Storey II, 263). The work is also known as the Khirqah. The scribe refers to himself as a descendant of the author's family, and dedicates the book to "the second ?a?ib Qiran," probably the Qajar king Na?ir al-Din Shah (r. 1848-96). The text covers topics of sexual health and reproduction, including infertility, manners and timing for copulation, determining the gender of fetuses, increasing sperm count, erectile function and enlargement, female sexuality (based on physical appearance of women), and curing a variety of ailments and discomforts. The recommendations almost always include the use of various potions, to be applied to the body or ingested.
    Additional descriptive data: Chapter headings and other divisions in red ink, text in black. The name "?akim-I Ma?i" is signed in ink on the spine, fore-edge, and front endpapers. On leaf 39b, next to chapter 13, a note in the margin reads "the description of the 13th chapter was not there and therefore was not written."
  - 15 Tarikh-i padshahan-i ?Ajam ... az ... Kiyumars ilá ... Fat? ?Ali Shah-i Qajar The history of Persian kings ... from ... Kiyumars to ... Fat? ?Ali Shah-i Qajar., [between 1797 and 1834] (Box 3, Folder 3)
    Physical Description: 175 leaves: paper; 217 x 114 mm. bound to 216 x 127 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Dynastic history of Iran, written during the reign of Fat? ?Ali Shah-I Qajar (r. 1797-1834). The manuscript includes a list of kings for each dynasty, and a brief summary of their most famous deeds. Possibly written by a member of the court elite, for use as a reference tool.
    * ff. 2a-4b: List of kings and dynasties. * ff.4b-15b: The Pishdadids (Kiyumarth to Alexander). * ff.16a-18a: The Party kings (From Alexander to Ardashir the Sasanian). * ff.18a-28b: Sasanians (Ardashir to Yazdgird III). * ff.28b-38a: The Arabs of Iraq and Syria (Banu Tamim, the Ghassanids, and the Himyarites). * ff.38b: Blank. * ff.39a-40b: List of kings from Mu?ammad to Fat?-?Ali Shah. * ff.41a-48b: From Mu?ammad to ?asan ibn ?Ali. * ff.49a-55a: The descendants of Mu?ammad (?usayn to Mu?ammad ibn al-?asan al-Mahdi). * ff.55b-: Blank. * ff.56a-59b: The Umayyids (Yazid to Marwan). * ff.60a-68b: Abbasids (Saffa? to al-Musta?sim). * ff.69a-90b: Kings contemporary with the Abbasids (?ahirids, ?affarids, Samanids, Ghaznawids, Ghurids, Buyids, Saljuqids. * ff.Khwarazm-Shahs, Ata Begs, Isma? ilis, Ayyubids, Qara Khi?a). * ff.90b-96b: The Mongols (Genghis Khan to Malik Ashraf). * ff.97a-106b: The party kings contemporary with the Mongols and after (Chupanids, Ilkayids, Amir Shaykh Abu al-?asan, Mu?affarids, Karts, Sarbadarids). * ff.107a-118b: The Gurakanids and Turcoman kings (Tamerlane and his descendants as well as Qara Quyunlu, Aq Quyunlu, Uzbeks). * ff.118b-134b: The ?afawids and Afghans. * ff.134b-148b: The Afsharids. * ff.149a-155b: The Zandids. * ff.155b-173b: The Qajars.
    Layout: Average 20 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Red leather binding, stamped in black and gilt.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black ink, in a red, gold, blue and black border.
  - 16 Tarjumah-i Farsi min la?ayif-i ma? navi The Persian translation of the spiritual pleasantries., 1761. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Physical Description: 129 leaves: paper; 180 x 110 mm. bound to 192 x 157 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Persian translation of an unidentified Turkish commentary on Maulana Jalal al-Din Rumi's Mas?avi. The manuscript begins well into Book 1, with the story of "The lion and the games" (verse 1186 of Nicholson's edition). The commentary does not follow the Mas?avi verse-to-verse, but proceeds selectively through the text. The final commentary is on verse 563 of Book 5, or the story of "The wise man and the peacock."
    * ff. 1a-28a: Book One. * ff. 28b-60b: Book Two. * ff. 60b-94b: Book Three. * ff. 94b-125a: Book Four. * ff. 125a-129b: Book Five.
    Layout: Average 21 lines of text per page, mostly diagonal.
    Binding: Soft black leather, blind stamped. The text block is entirely detached from its binding. Additional descriptive data: 16 quires, probably lacking quires from the beginning and end. Text in black ink, with verses and underlining often in red. Occasional staining and marginalia.
  - 17 Davazdah imam Twelve imams., [1897-1899] (Box 3, Folder 5)
    Author: Tu?i, Na?ir al-Din Mu?ammad ibn Mu?ammad, 1201-1274.
    Scribe: Mirza Mu?ammad ?Ali al-Arzinjani.
    Physical Description: 16 leaves: paper; 122 x 76 mm. bound to 126 x 80 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Short prayer by thirteenth-century Shiite scholar Na?ir al-Din Tusi, in an exemplary Naskh script. Dedicated by the scribe to the governor of Fars, ?Abd al-?usayn Mirza Farmanfarma.
    Decoration: Gilt applied to space between lines of text and borders (ff. 1b-2a.)
    Binding: Brown leather binding, stamped in green, with blue and yellow pastedowns.
    Additional descriptive data: Exquisite calligraphy, with most of the text in black ink. The name of God appears in red or blue, and the word "praise," followed by the name of the prophet or an imam in red ink. Dedication in red and blue ink.
  - 18 Zij Astronomical tables., 1827. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    Author: Tusi, Na?ir al-Din Mu?ammad ibn Mu?ammad, 1201-1274.
    Scribe: ?Ali ibn ?Abd al-Razzaq al-Tabrizi.
    Physical Description: 62 leaves: paper; 243 x 186 mm. bound to 247 x 189 mm.
    Scope and Content Note The manuscript contains three separate works, as indicated by a spine label stating, "Three books in one." The three texts are contained within seven parallel columns on each page, alternatively narrow (in red ink), and wide (in black ink). The two narrow columns set along the outer border of the pages contain single letters, and occasional pairs of letters; the two narrow internal columns consist of individual words. The text in the wider columns consists of complete sentences. The three compositions are written linearly within these columns throughout the extent of the manuscript, proceeding from page to page; one in the wider, black-ink columns, one in the outer narrow columns, and one in the inner narrow columns. A second hand, probably a former owner, has written the title "Tarikh dawlat rasuli" on the first leaf. The same title, in a different hand, is found on the fore-edge.
    Layout: Average 17 lines of text per page.
    Binding: Soft black leather with blue pastedowns.
    Additional descriptive data: Text in black, red, and orange ink; occasional stains.
  - 19 [Tarikh-i Va??af] [Va??af's history]., 1843. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Author: [Va??af al-?a??rat, ?Abd Allah ibn Fa?? Allah, 1264 or 5-1329?].
    Physical Description: 261 leaves: paper; 334 x 206 mm. bound to 350 x 212 mm.
    Scope and Content Note Volumes 1 and 2 from Va??af's 5-volume history of the Mongols, including histories of the Hülegu, Qublai and Arghun, in addition to the Salghurids of Fars. Incomplete, with missing quires.
    Layout: 17 lines of text per page.
    Additional descriptive data: Persian text in black, Arabic verses in red. Occasional marginalia and stains.